<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "book.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet href="book.css" type="text/css"?>
<!-- Source: http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/521 -->
<!-- Footnotes were added by Péter Jeszenszky. -->
<book>
	<author>Daniel Defoe</author>
	<title>The Life and Adventures of Robinson Crusoe</title>
	<chapter>
		<title>Start in Life</title>
		<para>I was born in the year 1632, in the city of York, of a good family, though not of that
			country, my father being a foreigner of Bremen, who settled first at Hull. He got a good
			estate by merchandise, and leaving off his trade, lived afterwards at York, from whence
			he had married my mother, whose relations were named Robinson, a very good family in
			that country, and from whom I was called Robinson Kreutznaer; but, by the usual
			corruption of words in England, we are now called—nay we call ourselves and write
			our name—Crusoe; and so my companions always called me.</para>
		<para>I had two elder brothers, one of whom was lieutenant-colonel to an English regiment of
			foot in Flanders, formerly commanded by the famous Colonel Lockhart<footnote>Sir William
				Lockhart of Lee (1621–1675)</footnote>, and was killed at the battle near
				Dunkirk<footnote>The Battle of the Dunes, also known as the Battle of Dunkirk, was
				fought on 14 June 1658.</footnote> against the Spaniards. What became of my second
			brother I never knew, any more than my father or mother knew what became of me.</para>
		<para>Being the third son of the family and not bred to any trade, my head began to be
			filled very early with rambling thoughts. My father, who was very ancient, had given me
			a competent share of learning, as far as house-education and a country free school
			generally go, and designed me for the law; but I would be satisfied with nothing but
			going to sea; and my inclination to this led me so strongly against the will, nay, the
			commands of my father, and against all the entreaties and persuasions of my mother and
			other friends, that there seemed to be something fatal in that propensity of nature,
			tending directly to the life of misery which was to befall me.</para>
		<!-- ... -->
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Slavery and Escape</title>
		<para>That evil influence which carried me first away from my father's house—which
			hurried me into the wild and indigested notion of raising my fortune, and that impressed
			those conceits so forcibly upon me as to make me deaf to all good advice, and to the
			entreaties and even the commands of my father—I say, the same influence, whatever
			it was, presented the most unfortunate of all enterprises to my view; and I went on
			board a vessel bound to the coast of Africa; or, as our sailors vulgarly called it, a
			voyage to Guinea.</para>
		<!-- ... -->
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Wrecked on a Desert Island</title>
		<para>After this stop, we made on to the southward continually for ten or twelve days,
			living very sparingly on our provisions, which began to abate very much, and going no
			oftener to the shore than we were obliged to for fresh water. My design in this was to
			make the river Gambia or Senegal, that is to say anywhere about the Cape de Verde, where
			I was in hopes to meet with some European ship; and if I did not, I knew not what course
			I had to take, but to seek for the islands, or perish there among the negroes. I knew
			that all the ships from Europe, which sailed either to the coast of Guinea or to Brazil,
			or to the East Indies, made this cape, or those islands; and, in a word, I put the whole
			of my fortune upon this single point, either that I must meet with some ship or must
			perish.</para>
		<para>When I had pursued this resolution about ten days longer, as I have said, I began to
			see that the land was inhabited; and in two or three places, as we sailed by, we saw
			people stand upon the shore to look at us; we could also perceive they were quite black
			and naked. I was once inclined to have gone on shore to them; but Xury was my better
			counsellor, and said to me, “No go, no go.” However, I hauled in nearer the
			shore that I might talk to them, and I found they ran along the shore by me a good way.
			I observed they had no weapons in their hand, except one, who had a long slender stick,
			which Xury said was a lance, and that they could throw them a great way with good aim;
			so I kept at a distance, but talked with them by signs as well as I could; and
			particularly made signs for something to eat: they beckoned to me to stop my boat, and
			they would fetch me some meat. Upon this I lowered the top of my sail and lay by, and
			two of them ran up into the country, and in less than half-an-hour came back, and
			brought with them two pieces of dried flesh and some corn, such as is the produce of
			their country; but we neither knew what the one or the other was; however, we were
			willing to accept it, but how to come at it was our next dispute, for I would not
			venture on shore to them, and they were as much afraid of us; but they took a safe way
			for us all, for they brought it to the shore and laid it down, and went and stood a
			great way off till we fetched it on board, and then came close to us again.</para>
		<!-- ... -->
	</chapter>
	<!-- ... -->
</book>
